<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The answer of the Parliament of England, to a paper, entituled, a declaration by the Kings Majesty, to his subjects of the kingdoms of Scotland, England and Ireland. Printed at Edinburgh, 1650. Whereunto is annexed, copies of four letters to the King of Scotland, which were found in the Lord Loudouns cabinet. Die Veneris, 20 Septem. 1650. Ordered by the Parliament, that this answer and letters be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82540</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E613_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206510</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865654</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865654</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82540)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E613[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The answer of the Parliament of England, to a paper, entituled, a declaration by the Kings Majesty, to his subjects of the kingdoms of Scotland, England and Ireland. Printed at Edinburgh, 1650. Whereunto is annexed, copies of four letters to the King of Scotland, which were found in the Lord Loudouns cabinet. Die Veneris, 20 Septem. 1650. Ordered by the Parliament, that this answer and letters be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>Loudoun, John Campbell, Earl of, 1598-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Husband and John Field, printer to the Parliament of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf consists of a coat-of-arms printed on the verso.</note>
                  <note>In part a reply to Charles II's Declaration by the Kings Majesty, to his subjects of the kingdoms of Scotland, England, and Ireland.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER OF THE Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> TO A PAPER,
Entituled, <hi>A Declaration by the Kings Majeſty, To His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the
Kingdoms of</hi> Scotland, England <hi>and</hi> Ireland. <hi>Printed at</hi>
Edinburgh, 1650.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed, COPIES of Four LETTERS To the King of
SCOTLAND, Which were found in the Lord <hi>Loudouns</hi> Cabinet.</p>
            <p> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license_to_print">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Veneris, 20 Septem.
1650.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ORdered by the Parliament, That this <hi>Anſwer</hi> and
<hi>Letters</hi> be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric.
Parliamenti.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Huſband</hi> and <hi>John
Field,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> 1650.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:117902:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117902:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117902:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117902:3"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>IT is well known unto the World, what maner of Conteſt the
Parliament of <hi>England</hi> hath had, theſe years laſt paſſed, in
their own Defence, to preſerve themſelves from the almoſt Eſtabliſh'd
Tyranny, which, through a long tract of Time, had been obtruding it ſelf, as
well over the Conſciences, as the Laws and Civil Liberties of the People in
<hi>England, Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> Deſigning and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing
the Extremity of all Evils upon theſe Nations, rather then to ſuffer it
ſelf to be ſtopped in its courſe, or diſappointed of its end: Elſe
what ſignified the firſt Troubles raiſed in <hi>Scotland</hi> by the late
King, and (that failing) then the cheriſhing, upholding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing, to
the laſt, the Horrid and Bloody Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the ſame
hand; and after all, the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an Unnatural War into the Bowels of this
Nation, managed and improved to the utmoſt by him, and the Popiſh,
Prelatical and Prophane Party ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to him therein? Which Evils have been
writ out in ſuch deep Characters of Blood, been attended with ſuch
Conſumption of Treaſure, and almoſt Devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſeveral Countries
in the three Nations, that they will not ſuddenly be worn out of the Peoples
Senſe, much leſs of their Memory. Yet, even during theſe firſt
Troubles, the Deſigners were not aſhamed to appear bare-faced, in their
open and avowed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, of Oppoſition and Hatred againſt the Cauſe
of God, the Work of Reformation, Priviledges of Parliament, and Peoples
Liberties; having for that <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117902:4"/>purpoſe incorporated
themſelves in Intereſt with all the known and implacable Enemies of the
ſame, as, The Popiſh Party abroad, and Prelatical and Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Party at
home: But now, when by the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Bleſſing of God unto this Nation,
Tyranny hath received its Mortal Wound, not onely by being Beaten out of the
Field, in all that have fought for it, but by the Remarkable Juſtice that
hath been done upon the Prime Inſtrument (in the late Kings Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and
in conſequence thereof, the Government of this Nation Reſtored to a
Commonwealth and Fee-State; and the Supreme Authority Eſtabliſh'd in this
and Succeſſive Parliaments, or Repreſentatives of the People, without
King or Houſe of Lords, as the beſt Means and ſtrongeſt Bulwark, under
the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, to preſerve the Peoples Liberties againſt the like
Attempts and Invaſions for time to come, and ſo deprived of all Hopes of
its ever taking Root again in this Commonwealth; and being like alſo, if this
Commonwealth continue, to loſe ground in <hi>Scotland</hi> and other Nations,
where the People are made meer Slaves and Vaſſals to the Will of their
Prince, and his Lordly Inſtruments in Church and State.</p>
               <p>It hath ſeemed good to <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> the Declared
King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to the prevailing Party in State and Kirk there,
to dreſs up this old and Malignant Cauſe, in a more plauſible and
Religious Garb, then that with which it was put forth before; and to take it
out of, or rather for a time ſuſpend its Exerciſe in the hands of the
Popiſh, Prelatical and Malignant Party, who begin alſo to ſee they can
keep it up no longer, but it will certainly breathe out its laſt Gaſp, 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117902:4"/>if it be not ſhifted, and by ſome Change of
Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, recover a Reputation amongſt good men; And therefore a room
and place is made by common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent amongſt them, to receive and hide the
Intereſt of Tyranny, and of Oppoſition to all Chriſtian, as well as Civil
Liberty, within the verges of the Solemn League and Covenant: The Signing of
which Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and the emitting of a Declaration, by the eldeſt Son of the
late King (expreſſing in words a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial Repentance, for what there
is no probability for him at the preſent to put in practice) and promiſing
(in effect) for the future, to Tyrannize and Enſlave men chiefly by the
Advice of the Kirk, and as ſhall tend to uphold their Power and
Clergy-Intereſt, in the firſt place, before his own (An Homage which the
Pope indeed hath claimed from Earthly Princes, as that which is due to him, as
he pretends himſelf Gods Vicar on Earth.) This is now accounted full
Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as to what is to be done on his part; and whereupon they would
make the World believe the ſtate of the Cauſe is altered, even to that
degree, as that their New King is now no longer upon his Old Principles, but is
come over to thoſe upon which they have fought againſt his Father for
theſe Twelve years paſt. The Deceit and Evil of all which, will appear,
when we ſhall come to take in pieces the ſaid Declaration, and thereby
Unmask (as we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed) the groſs Hypocriſie of the Contrivers
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the Wicked Deſign that is couched and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, under
pretence of The Name and Cauſe of God, The Work of Reformation, The Power and
Freedoms of Parliaments in <hi>England,</hi> according to <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117902:5"/>their Ancient Form (except onely a perpetual ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and
ſubordinating of their Laws, Councels and Advices to the Clergy, who have a
promiſe, That their Councels ſhall be heard before any other whatſoever)
and other plauſible Inducements to poſſeſs himſelf of the Crown of
<hi>England;</hi> And having obtained that Power, with the Deſtruction of all
the Faithful and truly godly Party, that have declared themſelves for this
preſent Government, He may then be more abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in Tyranny, then ever
Prince in <hi>England</hi> was, and derive the ſame in Succeſſion to his
Poſterity, upon the ſcore of Conqueſt, acquired to him by the help of the
<hi>Scots;</hi> whoſe good-will to <hi>England</hi> (for the Cauſe of God,
as they would have us believe) hath been and ſtill is ſuch, as to hold it
fit to impoſe upon us the Yoke of their Uſurpations both in Church and
State, and have not ſcrupled to attempt the attaining of the ſame, either
by Subtilty of by Force: By both which Means they never thought themſelves in
ſo fair a way unto their End, as now they have caſt themſelves into, by
their late Agreement with their New King; and this Declaration they have made
him put forth, which we ſhall Anſwer in the diſtinct Paragraphs of it in
order as they lie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1.</head>
               <q>HIs Majeſty taking in conſideration, that merciful
Diſpenſation of Divine Providence, by which he hath been recovered out of
the ſnare of Evil Councel; and having attained ſo full perſwaſion and
confidence of the Loyalty of his People in <hi>Scotland,</hi> with whom he hath
too long ſtood at a diſtance; and of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117902:5"/>of their Cauſe, as to joyn in one Covenant with them, and
to caſt himſelf and his Intereſts wholly upon God; and in all matters
Civil, to follow the Advice of his Parliament, and ſuch as ſhall be
intruſted by them, and in all matters Eccleſiaſtick, the Advice of the
Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly and their Commiſſioners; and being ſenſible of
his duty to God, and deſirous to approve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the conſciences of
all his good Subjects, and to ſtop the mouthes of his and their Enemies and
Tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, doth in reference to his former Deportments, and as to his
Reſolutions for the future, Declare as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</q>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <p>THe Diſpenſations of Divine Providence are indeed
merciful, by which Princes or Governors are at any time really recovered out of
the ſnare of evil Counſel; yet when this is done by the violence of an
abſolute Neceſſity, 'tis ſeldom real or laſting, and then the Mercy
in it is but little to the People, who will taſte the bitter fruit of ſuch
diſſimulations when it is too late. It ſeems that the King of
<hi>Scotland</hi> can now profeſs to the world, he hath been in the ſnare
of evil Counſel, whileſt he entertained any doubts or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the
loyalty of his People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſtood at a diſtance from
them and their Cauſe, and was unconvinced of the righteouſneſs of it, and
did not joyn in one Covenant with them, nor caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his
Intereſts wholly upon God; and in all matters Civil follow the advice of his
Parliament; and in all matters Eccleſiaſtick, the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, or
the Commiſſioners thereof: We do not deny <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117902:6"/>but his former
Counſels, as well as himſelf, have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great change, through the
merciful Diſpenſation of Divine Providence to this Commonwealth,
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpering ſo wonderfully our Armies in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
him and his Intereſt in a great meaſure from thence, and preſerving this
Nation in Peace within it ſelf, to prevent any footing to be given to him
here, whereby he was reduced to the courſe he hath now taken, to ſay what
the Parliament and Kirk of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhall put into his mouth, and
tell him is fit for him and his Affairs to declare, or elſe to loſe all:
And if <hi>Scotland</hi> do eſteem it ſo great a mercy, to have him reduced
to this pure neceſſity of caſting himſelf into their Arms; We know to
whom, under God, they owe the Obligation; a Bleſſing which we confeſs we
do not envy them, and which (were we ſecured never to be partaker of with
them, or by their means) we ſhould not hinder them from the free and full
enjoyment of; Having by fad experience found what it is to have a King, though
never ſo well beſet in appearance with good men about him, or to truſt to
his Repentances and Promiſes, Oaths or Declarations, how fair ſoever in
ſhew, and how ſtrong ſoever laid down in words. As to the Evil of the
Counſel, out of which its ſaid, He is recovered by this change: We ſay,
That if the future Reſolutions mentioned in this Declaration, be the
evidences whereby we are to judge of the goodneſs of the new Counſel, we
cannot but take notice, That they do onely vary the means, but not the end,
which ſtill is evil, to wit, The enſlaving the three Nations; and do change
the Inſtruments, but not the Cauſe (as is before, and ſhall further be
made evident) and <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117902:6"/>therefore we muſt be excuſed, if we
judge that their yong King is yet in as great a ſnare of evil Counſel as
ever, and thereupon endeavor what in us lies, to keep this Nation from falling
under the bad effects thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <q>THough his Majeſty as a dutiful Son be obliged to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the
memory of his Royal Father, and have in eſtimation the perſon of his
Mother; yet doth he deſire to be deeply humbled and afflicted in Spirit
before God, becauſe of his Fathers hearkning to, and following evil
Counſels, and his oppoſition to the work of Reformation, and to the Solemn
League and Covenant, by which ſo much of the blood of the Lords People hath
been ſhed in theſe Kingdoms; and for the Idolatry of his Mother, the
Toleration whereof in the Kings Houſe, as it was matter of great ſtumbling
to all the Proteſtant Churches, ſo could it not but be an high provocation
againſt him who is a jealous God, viſiting the ſins of the Fathers upon
the Children: And albeit, his Majeſty might extenuate his former Carriages
and Actions, in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the advice, and walking in the way of thoſe who
are oppoſite to the Covenant and to the work of God, and might excuſe his
delaying to give ſatisfaction to the juſt and neceſſary Deſires of
the Kirk and Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from his education, and age, and
evil Counſel, and Company, and from the ſtrange &amp; inſolent
proceedings of Sectaries againſt his Royal Father; and in reference to
Religion and the ancient Government of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> to
which he hath the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right of Succeſsion; yet knowing that he hath 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117902:7"/>to do with God, he doth ingeniouſly acknowledge all his
own ſins, and all the ſins of his Father Houſe, craving pardon, and
hoping for mercy and reconciliation through the blood of Jeſus Chriſt. And
as he doth value the conſtant Addreſſes that were made by his People to
the Throne of Grace on his behalf, when he ſtood in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Work
of God, as a ſingular Teſtimony of long-ſuffering, patience and mercy
upon the Lords part, and loyalty upon theirs; ſo doth he hope, and ſhall
take it as one of the greateſt tokens of their love and affection to him and
to his Government, That they will continue in Prayer and Supplication to God
for him; That the Lord, who ſpared and preſerved him to this day,
not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of all his own guiltineſs, may be at peace with him, and
give him to fear the Lord his God, and to ſerve him with a perfect heart and
with a willing minde all the days of his life.</q>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt Teſtimony of the good of the New Counſels,
into whoſe hands the <hi>Scots</hi> King hath caſt himſelf, is, The
Repentance towards God which they adviſe him to make, in reference to his own
Sins, and Sins of his Fathers Houſe; A matter in it ſelf truly
praiſe-worthy; and the conſequence whereof, in the words wherein it is
expreſs'd, doth in no ſmall meaſure reach to the Acknowledgement of the
juſt Hand of God upon his Father and Mother, in the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of the one,
and taking away the life of the other by the hand of Juſtice; putting it into
the hearts of thoſe here, that remained faithful to their Truſt in
Parliament, to cauſe his Blood to be poured <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117902:7"/>forth, by
whoſe perſonal Actings, Authority and Commiſſions, ſo much of the
Blood of the Lords People hath been ſhed in the Three Nations (as this
Declaration it ſelf acknowledges) and for which therefore we have reaſon to
bleſs God, and admire his Providence, That out of the mouth of the Son, there
hath, in the ſight of the whole World, been brought forth ſuch a
Juſtification of the Sentence paſſed and Executed upon the Father.</p>
                  <p>But as to the manner of Declaring this his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that
is to ſay, with the Qualifications therein allowed of; whereby, under the
pretence of a dutiful Son, He may ſtill retain in Memory his Fathers Actions
of Tyranny for his Patern; and, through the high Eſtimation of his Mother,
have his Ears ſtill open to her Councels, as often as ſhe can convey them
to him: And as ſenſible as he muſt be of his own and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Enmity
and Oppoſition againſt the Lords People in the Three Nations, yet he muſt
ſtill be encouraged to perſiſt in the ſame againſt thoſe that are
truly the Lords People, under the pretence of Sectaries. Theſe are ſuch
Inconſiſtencies and Haltings in ſo ſerious a Work, that as it is
juſtly to be feared, that God will not be well pleaſed therewith; ſo
neither will it have its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected effect amongſt men, who with eaſe may
ſee through the deceit and lameneſs of it, and will with greater abhorrency
be aware of them and their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, that ſtrive to cover themſelves with
Webs, that will not prove Garments, but whoſe Nakedneſs doth ſtill
appear.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:117902:8"/>
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <q>ANd his Majeſty having, upon full perſwaſion of the
Juſtice and Equity of all the Heads and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles thereof, now Sworn and
Subſcribed the National Covenant of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the
Solemn League and Covenant of the Three Kingdoms of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, England</hi>
and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Doth Declare, That he hath not Sworn and Subſcribed
theſe Covenants, and entred into the Oath of God with his People, upon any
ſiniſter Intention and crooked Deſign, for attaining his own Ends; but,
ſo far as Humane Weakneſs will permit, in the truth and ſincerity of his
heart: And that he is firmly Reſolved, in the Lords ſtrength, to adhere
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and to proſecute to the utmoſt of his power, all the Ends
thereof, in his Station and Calling, really, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and ſincerely all
the days of his life. In order to which, he doth in the firſt place Profeſs
and Declare, That he will have no Enemies, but the Enemies of the Covenant; and
that he will have no Friends, but the Friends of the Covenant: And therefore,
as he doth now deteſt and abhor all Popery, Superſtition and Idolatry,
together with Prelacy, and all Errors, Hereſie, Schiſm and Prophaneneſs,
and reſolves not to tolerate, much leſs allow any of theſe in any part of
his Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, but to oppoſe himſelf thereto, and to endeavor
the Externation thereof to the utmoſt of his power; ſo doth he as a
Chriſtian Exhort, and as a King Require, That all ſuch of his Subjects, who
have ſtood in Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Solemn League and Covenant, and Work of
Reformation, upon a pretence of Kingly Intereſt, or any other pretext
whatſoever, to lay down their Enmity <pb n="15" facs="tcp:117902:8"/>againſt the Cauſe
and People of God, and to ceaſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Intereſt of Man to the
Intereſt of God; which hath been one of thoſe things which hath
occaſioned many Troubles and Calamities in theſe Kingdoms, and being
inſiſted into, will be ſo far from Eſtabliſhing of the Kings Throne,
that it will prove an Idol of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, to provoke unto wrath him who is
King of kings, and Lord of lords. The King ſhall always eſteem them beſt
Servants, and moſt Loyal Subjects, who ſerve him, and ſeek his
Greatneſs in a right line of ſubordination unto God; <hi>Giving unto God
the things that are Gods, and unto Ceſar the things that are Ceſars:</hi>
And Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth, not to love or countenance any who have ſo little
Conſcience and Piety, as to follow his Intereſts with a prejudice to the
Goſpel and the Kingdom of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which he looks not upon as a
duty, but as flattery, and driving of Self-Deſigns, under a pretence of
maintaining Royal Authority and Greatneſs. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> His Majeſty
being convinced in Conſcience of the exceeding great Sinfulneſs and
Unlawfulneſs of that Treaty and Peace made with the Bloody <hi>Iriſh</hi>
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, who treacherouſly ſhed the Blood of ſo many of his faithful and
Loyal Subjects in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing unto them the Liberty of
the Popiſh Religion; for the which he doth from his heart deſire to be
deeply humbled before the Lord: And likewiſe conſidering how many Breaches
have been upon their part, Doth Declare the ſame to be void, and that his
Majeſty is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved therefrom; being truly ſorry that he ſhould have
ſought unto ſo unlawful Help for Reſtoring of him to his Throne, and
reſolving, for the time to come, rather to chooſe Affliction then Sin.
<hi>Thirdly,</hi> As his <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117902:9"/>Majeſty did in the late Treaty
with his people in this Kingdom, agree to recal and annul all Commiſsions
againſt any of his Subjects who did adhere to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Monarchical
Government in any of his Kingdoms: So doth he now Declare, That by
Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionating of ſome perſons by Sea againſt the people of
<hi>England,</hi> he did not intend Damage or Injury to his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt and
harmleſs Subjects in that Kingdom, who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Trade of Merchandize in
their lawful Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, but onely the oppoſing and ſuppreſsing of thoſe
who had Uſurped the Government; and not onely bar him from his juſt Right,
but alſo Exerciſe an Arbitrary Power over his people, in thoſe things
which concern their Perſons, Conſciences and Eſtates: And as ſince his
coming into <hi>Scotland</hi> he hath given no Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions againſt any
of his Subjects in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo he doth hereby
Aſſure and Declare, That he will give none to their prejudice or damage;
and whatever ſhall be the Wrongs of theſe Uſurpers, That he will be ſo
far from avenging theſe upon any who are free thereof, by interrupting or
ſtopping the liberty of Trade and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, or otherwiſe, That he will
ſeek their good, and to the utmoſt imploy his Royal Power, That they may be
protected and defended againſt the unjuſt Violence of all men whatſoever.
And albeit his Majeſty deſires to conſtruct well of the Intentions of
thoſe (in reference to his Majeſty) who have been active in Councel or Arms
againſt the Covenant; yet, being convinced that it doth conduce for the Honor
of God, the good of his Cauſe, and his own Honor and Happineſs, and for the
Peace and Safety of theſe Kingdoms, That ſuch be not employed in places of
Power and Truſt, He doth De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117902:9"/>That he will not
employ, nor give Commiſsions to any ſuch, until they have not onely taken,
or renewed the Covenant, but alſo have given ſufficient Evidences of their
Integrity, Carriage and Affection to the Work of Reformation, and ſhall be
declared capable of Truſt by the Parliament of either Kingdom reſpective:
And His Majeſty, upon the ſame grounds, doth hereby recal all Commiſsions
given to any ſuch perſons; conceiving all ſuch perſons will ſo much
tender a good Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betwixt him and his Subjects, and the ſetling
and preſerving a firm Peace in theſe Kingdoms, That they will not grudge
nor repine at his Majeſties Reſolutions and Proceedings herein, much leſs
upon diſcontent act any thing in a divided way, unto the raiſing of New
Troubles, eſpecially ſince upon their pious and good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, there is
a Regreſs left unto them in maner above expreſs'd.</q>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>IT is ſomewhat early days for him, who (by reaſon of his
education and age, and the Councel and Company hitherto about him) could not be
much furthered into the ſight of the Juſtice and Equity of what is
contained in the Covenants mentioned, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, that is to ſay, in the
ſpace of almoſt four and twenty hours, to grow up into the full
perſwaſion of the Juſtice and Equity of all the Heads and Articles of
thoſe Covenants, and to be able to declare, That he hath not ſworn nor
ſubſcribed them upon any ſiniſter intention and crooked Deſign, for
attaining his own ends; and with ſo fix'd a Reſolution to perſiſt
therein really, conſtantly and ſincerely all the days of his 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117902:10"/>life; when as the Commiſſioners of the General
Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, in their Declaration dated the thirteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi>
do ſay, <hi>That there may be juſt Grounds of ſtumbling from his
refuſing to emit this Declaration;</hi> and do tell him in ſo many words,
that <hi>They will not own him nor his Intereſt, otherwiſe then with a
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to God, and in ſo far as he owns and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes the
Cauſe of God, and diſclaims his and his Fathers oppoſition to the Work of
God, and to the Govenant, and all the Enemies thereof: And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
all, he ſtill perſiſts in his Refufal, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing to</hi> Dunfermlyn,
<hi>whether the Marqueſs of</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyle <hi>and Earl of</hi> Lothian <hi>are
ſent after to preſs him to Subſcribe;</hi> and in the mean time,
overtures are made under-hand to our Army, as if things might yet be made up in
a fair way, and their King and they were not likely to agree: And on the
<hi>fifteenth of</hi> Auguſt, <hi>a Remonſtrance and Supplication of the
Officers of the Scots Army,</hi> by way ſeconding <hi>the foreſaid
Declaration of the Committee of Eſtates, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners of the General
Aſſembly,</hi> was <hi>preſented to, and approved of by the Committee of
Eſtates:</hi> And on the <hi>ſixteenth</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Auguſt, the
Declaration</hi> ſo earneſtly preſſed upon him, or rather forcibly
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted from him, is ſubſcribed and emited by him: And now in a moment,
what a bleſſed and hopeful change is wrought upon this yong King? how
hearty is he become to the Cauſe of God, and the work of Reformation? and how
readily doth he ſwallow down theſe bitter Pills which are prepared for and
urged upon him, as neceſſary to effect that deſperate cure under which
his Affairs lie? But who ſees not <pb n="19" facs="tcp:117902:10"/>the groſs
Hypocriſie of this whole Tranſaction, and the ſandy and rotten foundation
of all the Reſolutions flowing hereupon? as firſt, He that on the fifteenth
of <hi>Auguſt</hi> hugg'd all his Malignant and Popiſh Party in his
boſom, and lodged them in the ſecret Reſerves of his favor and love as
his beſt Friends, can now on the ſixteenth (the day following) from a
fulneſs of perſwaſion of the Juſtice and Equity of all the Heads and
Articles of the Covenant, renounce and diſcard them in the ſight of God and
the world, and vow ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have any more to do with them, as old Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
unleſs they by his example turn to be as good Converts as himſelf, and be
able to perſonate and act the ſame part; and ſo by vertue of the very
Covenant it ſelf, eat out and undermine thoſe who conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and
honeſtly intend the ends of it: The ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience whereof, was as well
ſeen in the managing the whole buſineſs of Duke <hi>Hamiltons</hi>
Invaſion, as in many of the then Members in both Houſes, who never ſhewed
more zeal for the Covenant, then when they found that thereby they could
ſuppreſs and beat down the truly godly and honeſt Party, as Sectaries,
and Enemies to Monarchical Government, and buoy up the ſinking and loſt
Reputations of the moſt engaged Royaliſts and rotten hearted Apoſtates,
under pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that they were turned Friends to the work of Reformation, and
for upholding the Church Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt: And if in this ſenſe the Scots King
will have no Enemies, but the Enemies of the Covenant, nor no Friends, but the
Friends of the Covenant, he makes but little change; for he hath the ſame
Friends and Enemies that he had before, with this onely difference, 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117902:11"/>That by his and his Parties becoming in appearance friends
to the Covenant for a while, they have the opportunity at the laſt to make
uſe of this Engine; better to undermine and oppoſe the true ends of the
Covenant, then by a flat oppoſition to it, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Crown, what
Diſſimulation is not thought lawful by Politicians? though a larger
meaſure then what is held forth in this Declaration, cannot eaſily be
inſtanced in; And which therefore we doubt not but God, who is the Searcher
of the Hearts, and Tryer of the Reyns, will proceed further to diſcover in
the face of the Sun, and more ſeverely judge in this new King of Scots and
his Houſe, then if he had dealt plainly with God and Man, and held himſelf
forth in his own colours: The little time which he hath been upon the Stage,
having ſufficiently laid him open what he is, A true Inheritor of his Fathers
Principles and Counſels, wherein he may be traced all along; and even in this
laſt Action, wherein he hath trod in the ſteps of his Father, as well as
other his Predeceſſors, who when ever they found themſelves in
<hi>Scotland</hi> beſet with the power of the Kirk and State, did
ſubſcribe and emit whatever was preſſed upon them, though they
reſolved to break all that ever was ſo done by them upon the firſt
occaſion.</p>
                  <p>And as a ſecond Deduction from his full perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of
the Juſtice and Equity of all the Heads and Articles of the Covenants, He
Declares his convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in conſcience of the exceeding great Sinfulneſs
and Unlawfulneſs of that Treaty and Peace made with the Bloody
<hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, and of allowing to them the liberty of the Popiſh
Religion; and that he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, <pb n="21" facs="tcp:117902:11"/>for time to come,
rather to chooſe Affliction then Sin. It ſeems very much to be doubted, if
the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Clogher,</hi> armed with a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
from <hi>Ormond, Charls Stuart</hi>'s pretended Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of
<hi>Ireland,</hi> had with his Army of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Popiſh Rebels,
founded upon a pure Popiſh Accompt, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded and prevailed againſt our
Army in <hi>Ulſter</hi> under Sir <hi>Charls Coot,</hi> Whether then that
which is now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and reſolved againſt as Sinful and Unlawful,
would have been ſo acknowledged, or thought wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, perhaps, ſo to have
been, by the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> it ſelf; conſidering that the ſaid
Biſhop offered very fair Quarter to all of the <hi>Scots</hi> Nation, that
were for Monarchical Government; and the <hi>Scots</hi> Clergy in thoſe parts
had about the ſame time ſtirr'd up the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in our Quarters to Mutiny
and Rebellion (inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that Sir <hi>Charls Coot</hi> was neceſſitated
to ſecure their perſons) as if they had done it on purpoſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
the way to uſher in the Infal upon our Quarters, to deſtroy our Forces, by
that <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, who pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Oppoſition chiefly againſt
ſuch as they call'd Sectaries, being indeed ſuch as declared for the
Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi> But when Sin doth not
proſper, it is no wonder if it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed; and if it loſe its power, it
is no marvel if it loſe alſo its credit, even with the beſt Friends to
it. It is fit Popery, and the Bloody Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhould be
renounced, and the <hi>Scots</hi> King Abſolved from any further hand in it
(conſidering the many Breaches, or rather Failings on their parts) now that
through the Bleſſing of God upon the Sectarian Army in that Nation, as they
call them, the Rebels <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117902:12"/>have been diſinabled to keep
themſelves in Power, and maintain his Intereſt there; which we have good
reaſon to believe is yet a greater Affliction to him, in his ſober
thoughts, then he findes it to be Sin: For, as we are credibly informed,
<hi>Ormond</hi> and <hi>Inchiquin</hi> were very lately departing out of
<hi>Ireland,</hi> and giving up all there; but by very freſh Directions and
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands from the <hi>Scots</hi> King out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they are
Required to ſtay, and promote his Intereſt there: In purſuance of which,
the ſaid <hi>Ormond</hi> is as buſie as ever, giving out Commiſſions
amongſt the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whether as Friends to the Covenant or no, we
ſhall leave the World to judge.</p>
                  <p>The third and laſt Effect of the <hi>Scots</hi> Kings full
perſwaſion of the Juſtice and Equity of all the Heads and Articles of the
Covenant, is, His Recalling all Commiſſions formerly given for infeſting
the Seas with Pyracies and Depraedations; and Reſolutions for the future, to
employ none in ſuch Power and Truſt, until they have renewed the Covenant,
and be declared capable of ſuch Truſt by the Parliament, as more at large
is afore-recited in the clauſe it ſelf. It is to be obſerved (as little
Juſtice and Neceſſity as the <hi>Scots</hi> pretend there was of
ſending our Army into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) That here is now acknowledged by
their King, for himſelf and them alſo, That the <hi>Scots</hi> have
treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and concluded with their King, on the behalf of the People of
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as well as <hi>Scotland,</hi> and have
taken upon them (we preſume, by vertue of the Covenant) to Intereſt
themſelves, in the higheſt Degree, in the Laws and Liberties of
<hi>England,</hi> and have laid the Ground-work of a New War, to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117902:12"/>on principally by themſelves in this Nation, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring
for ſuch as adhere to the Covenant and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Government, and againſt
ſuch as (without Oppoſition to the Covenant) are for this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as
it is now Eſtabliſhed, without King or Houſe of Lords; And yet have the
confidence to Appeal to God, how innocent they are of giving us any cauſe to
ſend an Army into <hi>Scotland,</hi> in our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and to keep off this
deep deſigned War from our own Doors, as long, at leaſt, as God ſhall
enable us thereunto. Will not God judge ſuch under-hand Dealing as this? We
are aſſured he will; as he hath begun already of late moſt wonderfully
and ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to do: And he that thus brings it to light out of their own
mouthes, gives us hope, That in his due time he will return it with Shame and
Loſs upon their own heads, who have adventured on ſuch bold Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings,
to which they were never called, but are moſt perfectly unconcerned, any
further then they are drawn and inticed thereunto by inordinate luſting after
the Conqueſt of this Nation, and Eſtabliſhing themſelves in the Wealth
and Power thereof.</p>
                  <p>But to make all fair and ſmooth to thoſe that are apt to
be deluded and miſ-led, and to engage them in a New War againſt their
Native Countrey, their New Converted King declares, That by
Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating perſons at Sea to commit Pyracy and Deprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, for
the interruption of Trade, He intends no Damage nor Injury to his harmleſs
&amp; oppreſſed Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but onely to his Enemies; which now are none,
but thoſe that are Enemies to the Covenant and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Government: And
that he reſolves to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117902:13"/>none in ſuch Truſt, until
they have renewed the Covenant, and been declared capable of that Truſt by
Parliament; and therefore doth in words recal all Commiſſions given to any
ſuch perſons: But when all this is done, how are the former Evils committed
at Sea, to the interruption and deſtruction of Trade, remedied by this, or
the parties injured, repaired? When War was acted by Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi>
upon the Lives and Eſtates of this Nation, and none therein were employed,
but ſuch as took the Covenant, and were declared fit for that Truſt by the
Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who commanded that Invaſion, Were the Evils
of War leſs upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or the Crime leſs in thoſe that
acted them? Do ſuch Reſolutions as theſe vary the ſtate of the War, and
of the Cauſe, or do they onely change the Method and Circumſtances of
moving and proceeding to the ſame end? We hope it is too late now, to
miſ-lead any of the well-affected with Blindes of this nature, by which they
have once been cozened before, and whereby they may aſſure themſelves
they ſhall be deceived a ſecond time, if the Cavaliers, and purely Royal
Party, do but lay hold of the expedient offered to them, which is, by a
(faigned) pious and good Deportment, to make themſelves capable of a
Regreſs into their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Employments, upon the cheap Terms of ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
down the Covenant, and the obtaining the Approbation of as full and free a
Parliament, as that which Authorized the Invaſion of this Nation by Duke
<hi>Hamilton.</hi> And full, who knows not what ſuch a Declaration as this
ſignifies, to thoſe that have Commiſſions to Rob and Spoil, and perhaps
better <pb n="25" facs="tcp:117902:13"/>underſtand <hi>Charls Stuarts</hi> Intentions that
granted them, then thoſe that put him upon holding forth this
Diſſimulation, as if they were recalled.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <q>ANd as his Majeſty hath given ſatisfaction to the juſt and
neceſſary Deſires of the Kirk and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo
doth he hereby aſſure and declare, That he is no leſs willing and
deſirous to give ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the juſt and neceſſary Deſires of
his good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and in token
thereof, if the Houſes of Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> ſitting in
Freedom, ſhall think fit to preſent unto him the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of Peace,
agreed upon by both Kingdoms, he will not onely accord to the ſame, and
ſuch alterations thereanent, as the Houſes of Parliament, in regard of the
Conſtitution of Affairs, and the good of his Majeſty and his Kingdoms,
ſhall judge neceſſary, but do what is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary for
proſecuting the ends of the Solemn League and Covenant, eſpecially in
thoſe things which concern the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government; That not onely the
Directory of Worſhip, the Confeſsion of Faith, and Catechiſm, but alſo
the Propoſitions and Directory for Church-Government, accorded upon by the
Synod of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> may be ſetled; and that the
Church of <hi>England</hi> may enjoy the full Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Freedom of all
Aſſemblies, and Power of Kirk-Cenſures, and of all the Ordinances of
Jeſus Chriſt, according to the Rule of his own Word: And that whatſoever
is commanded by the God of Heaven, may be diligently done for the Houſe of
the God of Heaven; <pb n="26" facs="tcp:117902:14"/>and, whatever heretofore hath been the
ſuggeſtions of ſome to him, to render his Majeſty jealous of his
Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and of the Servants of God: Yet is he hath declared, that in
<hi>Scotland</hi> he will hearken to their Counſel, and follow their Advice
in thoſe things that concern that Kingdom and Kirk; So doth he alſo
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his firm Reſolution to manage the Government of the Kingdom of
<hi>England</hi> by the Advice of his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſiſting of an Houſe
of Lords and of an Houſe of Commons there; and in thoſe things that concern
Religion, to prefer the Counſels of the Miniſters of the Goſpel to all
other Counſels whatſoever. And that all the world may ſee how much he
tenders the ſafety of his People, and how precious their blood is in his
ſight, and how deſirous he is to recover his Crown and Government in
<hi>England</hi> by peaceable means; as he doth eſteem the ſervice of
thoſe who firſt engaged in the Covenant, and have ſince that time
faithfully fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the ends thereof, to be Duty to God, and Loyalty to him;
ſo is he willing, in regard of others who have been involved in theſe late
Commotions in <hi>England,</hi> againſt Religion and Government, to paſs an
Act of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, excepting onely ſome few in that Nation who have been chief
obſtructers of the work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and chief Authors of the change of
the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and of the Murther of his Royal Father. Provided, That theſe
who are to have the benefit of this Act, lay down Arms, and return unto the
obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their lawful Soveraign.</q>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:117902:14"/>
                  <head>ANSVVER.</head>
                  <p>THe Treaty that was touched upon in the former Paragraph, made
between the kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> and their King, in reference to
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> is here at large, and in the particulars
of it, ſet down; it will be needleſs to repeat them: In the whole Frame of
which, we dare boldly affirm, There are thoſe Grounds laid of inſlaving
this Nation to the Scots, and eſpecially to the power of their Clergy, That
no Parliament that hath ever yet ſate in <hi>England,</hi> &amp; have had the
leaſt drop of true Engliſh blood in them, but would diſdain and abhor to
be thus impoſed upon by the Scotiſh Nation: And are theſe the hopes that
are given to this Nation, of having two Houſes of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament ſitting in
Freedom, when what they muſt deſire, and what they muſt have, muſt be
prepared and agreed for them by a Forraign Nation? Will the Parliament be more
the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> when two Houſes ſhall be brought upon
the Stage again with a King at the Head of them, by the power of a Scotiſh
Army en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing this upon the Nation, then when the Parliament is in actual
poſſeſſion of ſuch Power and Freedom, as through the bleſſing of
God upon their endeavors, they are able by Law to exclude both King and Houſe
of Lords (the known oppoſers of the Peoples Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) out of their National
Counſels, and by the force God hath enabled them with, to preſerve the
common Peace and Safety of the whole, under the Government of a Commonwealth
and Free-State? It is too late now to think that the People have no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
diſcernment of their own true Intereſt, then to be <pb n="28" facs="tcp:117902:15"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atched with any ſatisfaction that can
be offered and given by a King, if he himſelf with his power muſt come in
at the end of it: Nor will the great promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of what he will do in the
Cauſe of God and Work of Reformation (under that pretence to let in upon us
the return again of Tyranny) much work upon the pious and judicious among us,
who want not the full and free enjoyments of their conſciences in this kinde,
in a voluntary way under this Government, without being beholding to the
Conceſſions of a King: nay, we may truly ſay, That ſince the change of
Government in this Nation, there have been more Laws made, and means uſed for
the propagating the Goſpel and the power of godlineſs, and encouraging the
true Profeſſors thereof; and more done for the extirpation of
Prophaneneſs and open Wickedneſs, then hath been during the whole time of
the Reigns of Kings over this Nation.</p>
                  <p>And as to the King of <hi>Scotland</hi>'s declaring his firm
Reſolution to manage the Government of <hi>England</hi> by the Advice of his
Parliament, conſiſting of a Houſe of Lords and of a Houſe of Commons;
and in thoſe things that concern Religion, to prefer the Counſel of the
Miniſters of the Goſpel, before all Counſels whatſoever; We truſt it
ſhall never be in his, nor in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotlands</hi> power, to
impoſe either himſelf or his Creatures, the Houſe of Lords, upon the
Supreme Authority and National Counſel of the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born People of
<hi>England;</hi> who, if they once become corrupted in that which is the
Fountain of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, their own Repreſentatives in Parliament
aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled (which with thus much coſt &amp; hazard are ſet up in 
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117902:15"/>ſome meaſure already in their Primitive and Original
Purity, and are going on every day more and more to the compleating thereof)
muſt expect nothing but the flowings forth of Tyranny and Miſchief upon
them, in and by their very Laws; and that which ſhould be the chief and onely
remedy againſt all their evils, would by this means become the greateſt
cauſe and author of them: Nor would this at all be mended or helped by the
Clauſe which is put in, That in thoſe things which concern Religion, he
will prefer the Counſels of the Miniſters of the Goſpel before all
Counſels whatſoever, and ſo by undenyable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence before the
Parliament it ſelf; for we have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by experience, That there is hardly
any Debate had in Parliament, but the ſubject-matter of it, in ſome
ſenſe or other, may be brought under the concernment of Religion, and by
that means, all the Laws muſt be or not be, as the Clergy will approve or not
approve of them; A practice ſo inconſiſtent with the Fundamental
Priviledges and Freedom of Parliament, and the Peoples good, that it hath
always been exploded and reſiſted by all Aſſertors of Engliſh
Freedom; and whenever any viſible Attempts have been made to promote ſuch a
Deſign (as too often have been ſince the ſitting of this Parliament) the
Parliaments have highly Reſented it, and frequently adjudged it High
Treaſon, looking at it, as that which Introduces a Forraign Juriſdiction,
and makes way for the ſetting up again a Popiſh Supremacy, changed in Name
onely.</p>
                  <p>Touching the Act of Oblivion offered; It is no doubt, the
effect of a great deſire the King of <hi>Scots</hi> 
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:117902:16"/>hath
to receive that which he pretends unto, in the Government of <hi>England,</hi>
An Acknowledgement of his Power to diſpenſe ſuch Favors: But in the mean
time we muſt obſerve, who it is that makes this Offer, A Traytor to the
Parliament and People of <hi>England,</hi> and who by his paſt Actings
againſt them, hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himſelf obnoxious to their ſevereſt
Cenſures, from which we hold him no way Abſolved by Aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption or
Declaration of a <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Kingſhip.</p>
                  <p>He who by Law and his Guilt ſtands incapable of the
meaneſt Priviledge amongſt us, Doth he think himſelf qualified to
Exerciſe the Greateſt? Shall the Malefactor be preſumed to have Power to
give Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to his Judge? Or do the <hi>Scots</hi> or their King ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine,
under pretence of an Act of Oblivion, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>England</hi> to receive
their Laws from <hi>Scotland?</hi> The Obſtructers of real Reformation we are
as much againſt, as he or they can pretend to be, as by our Acts and Actions
appears; Amongſt which, we reckon it not the leaſt, That that Grand Enemy
to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, the Father of the now Declarer, after his long and Bloody
progreſs made in Deſtruction and Devaſtation of the Innocent people in
the Three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (the Guilt whereof upon him, being a Truth ſo apparant, as
both Himſelf and Son, and our now Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Scotland,</hi> have been
forced to acknowledge) hath been by Our Authority Tryed, Adjudged and Executed,
for his notorious Treaſons, Tyrannies and Murthers; whereof, whatever the
Interpretation be given by the Son of that Murtherer, or other his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizans,
Old or New Malignants, late Apoſtates, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Neutrals, who ſtile
the Act of Juſtice, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb n="31" facs="tcp:117902:16"/>(with like Truth and
Reaſon, as thoſe who call Good, <hi>Evil,</hi> and Evil, <hi>Good;</hi>
Light, <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> and Darkneſs, <hi>Light</hi>) We, for our parts,
bleſs God for that opportunity put into our hands, of offering that Sacrifice
to Divine Juſtice, towards vindication and cleanſing of our Land from that
Blood, wherewith, by that Murtherer and his party, it was ſo miſerably
defiled. And as we have been obliged in a faithful and conſcientious
diſcharge of that Power and Truſt committed to us by God, and the People of
this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to Avenge that Innocent Blood upon the Head of that Tyrant, and
ſome others, the chief Authots and Actors under him in ſhedding thereof: So
for the ſeduced Multitude, and thoſe who in ſimplicity have been
miſguided by them, to act to their own and Countreys ruine, We have, in the
view of all, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our tenderneſs and forbearance towards them. And
being inveſted with the Authority of the Nation (whoſe Repreſentative we
are) in that behalf, as to ſuch miſ-led perſons, The Parliament of
<hi>England</hi> thinks fit further to declare, That as they have already long
ſince had it in their thoughts, and for that purpoſe have under
conſideration, <hi>An Act of general Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> (in the progreſs whereof
they have been interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the renewed Endeavors of <hi>Charls
Stuart,</hi> and his Adherents, to diſturb the Peace of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
and hinder its Settlement) they will with all convenient ſpeed apply
themſelves to the paſſing of ſuch an Act; And in the mean time do
expect from all perſons living under the Protection of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
That they make not themſelves any way Ayders or Abettors of the ſaid
<hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> in his <pb n="32" facs="tcp:117902:17"/>Pretences to the Government
of this Nation, under what fair and ſpecious ſhews ſoever, upon the
penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Laws in that behalf provided.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <q>THe Committee of Eſtates of the Kingdom, and General
Aſſembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> having declared ſo fully in
what concerns the Sectaries, and the preſent Deſigns, Reſolutions and
Actings of their Army againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And the
ſame Committee and Aſſembly having ſufficiently laid open publique
Dangers and Duties, both upon the right hand and upon the left, It is not
needful for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to adde any thing thereunto; except, That in thoſe
things he doth commend and approve them, and that he Reſolves to live and dye
with them, and his Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, in proſecution of the Ends of the
Covenant.</q>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>THe Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo their Army,
having ſo fully declared the Juſtice, Neceſſity and Ends of undertaking
the preſent Expedition into <hi>Scotland;</hi> and having alſo put it in a
way how thoſe Declarations from the Committee of Eſtates, and
Commiſſion of the Kirk, in Anſwer thereunto, ſhall have their
invalidity detected (as ſome of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in part have been) It will be
needleſs to ſay any thing further on this ſubject in this place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <q>ANd whereas that prevailing party in <hi>England,</hi> after all
their ſtrange Uſurpations, and inſolent <pb n="33" facs="tcp:117902:17"/>Actings in
that Land, Do not onely keep his Majeſty from the Government of that Kingdom
by force of Arms, but alſo have now Invaded the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
who have deſerved better things at their hands, and againſt whom they have
no juſt quarrel; His Majeſty doth therefore deſire and expect, That all
his good Subjects in <hi>England,</hi> who are and reſolve to be faithful to
God and to their King, according to the Covenant, will lay hold upon ſuch an
opportunity, and uſe their utmoſt endeavors to promove the Covenant, and
all the ends thereof; and to recover and re-eſtabliſh the Ancient
Government of the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> (under which, for many
Generations, it did flouriſh in peace and plenty at home, and in Reputation
abroad) and Priviledges of the Parliament, and Native and Juſt Liberty of the
People: His Majeſty deſires to aſſure himſelf, That there doth remain
in theſe ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of their Duty to Religion, their King and
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and ſo many ſparkles of the ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Valor,
which ſhined ſo eminently in their Noble Anceſtors, as will put them on
to beſtir themſelves for the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Yoke of thoſe mens
Oppreſsions from off their Necks: Shall men of Conſcience and Honor ſet
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Liberties and Government at ſo low a Rate, as not rather to
undergo any hazard, before they be thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of them? Will not all
generous men count any Death more tolerable, then to live in ſervitude all
their days? And will not Poſterity blame thoſe who dare attempt nothing for
themſelves, and for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in ſo good a Cauſe, in ſuch an
Exigent? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if they gather themſelves, and take courage, putting on a
Reſolution anſwerable to ſo Noble and juſt an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, they
ſhall honor God, and gain themſelves the <pb n="34" facs="tcp:117902:18"/>Reputation of
Pious men, worthy Patriots, and Loyal Subjects, and be called <hi>The Repairers
of the Breach,</hi> by the preſent and ſucceeding Generations; and they may
certainly promiſe to themſelves a Bleſsing from God upon ſo juſt and
honorable undertaking for the Lord, and for his Cauſe, for their own
Liberties, their Native King and Countrey, and the unvaluable good and
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Poſterity. Whatever hath formerly been his Majeſties
guiltineſs before God, and the bad ſucceſs that theſe have had who
owned his Affairs, whileſt he ſtood in Oppoſition to the Work of God; yet
the ſtate of the queſtion being now altered, and his Majeſty having
obtained Mercy to be on Gods ſide, and to prefer Gods Intereſt before his
own, He hopes, That the Lord will be gracious, and countenance his own Cauſe
in the hands of weak and ſinful Inſtruments, againſt all Enemies
what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. This is all that can be ſaid by his Majeſty at preſent, to
thoſe in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> at ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and
as they ſhall acquit themſelves at this time in the active diſcharge of
their neceſſary Duties, ſo ſhall they be accepted before God, indeared
to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and their Names had in remembrance throughout the World.
Given at Our Court at <hi>Dunfirmlin</hi> the ſixteenth day of <hi>Auguſt,
1650.</hi> and in the ſecond year of our Raign.</q>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>THat which was firſt in Deſign and lurking at the bottom,
is now laſt brought forth into open view to be put into practice: Until the
Scots King had thus waſhed himſelf clean with his verbal Repentances, had
pretended a full perſwaſion of the Juſtice and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of all the
Articles and Heads of the Covenant, <pb n="35" facs="tcp:117902:18"/>and a caſting of
himſelf wholly upon the Advice of Parliaments, &amp; Aſſemblies of
Divines, in all Civil and Eccleſiaſtical matters in both Nations; He would
have ſpoiled his own Affairs, and weakned the hands of all that ſhould have
joyned with him, to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in a new War againſt <hi>England,</hi> who
have ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſuffered too much already by the old; but now, after the
Landſcip of ſuch Wonders as theſe is drawn forth into a piece of paper,
and the ſtate of the Cauſe and of the War would ſeem to be changed, What
doth all this tend to, and what is the uſe that is to be made of it? Surely
no other then that, which if all theſe things had been left undone, was his
and the Scots proper Intereſt before, upon their old Accompt; that is to
ſay, To ſtir up all Parties and Intereſts capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his or their
ſeducements, to take the firſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to embroyl this Nation afreſh
in blood, that they might come in as Conquerors, and ſo make it, as much as
in them lies, the ſaddeſt ſpectacle of ruine and miſery that can be
imagined; for what can be like an over-running of the Nation by a Scotiſh
Army, with their King in the Head of them, be their pretences what they will?
And therefore, ſince it is ſo apparant what is the end and Deſign of this
Declaration, It will become all true Engliſhmen to be more awakened then
ever, to watch againſt, and reſiſt to the laſt man, ſo pernicious and
deep laid a Deſign, whereby at one blow to cut off and diſappoint all that
hath been fought for ſo many years together, and ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to
the power of a Forraign Nation, againſt whom God hath been pleaſed to give
ſo wonderful a Teſtimony by the late ſignal Victory near <hi>Dunbar,</hi>
the third of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and 
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117902:19"/>fifty, upon Solemn Appeals made by both parties to Almighty
God: And as it ſhall be our parts to omit no good means that God hath put
into our hands, to prevent any Inſurrections or Diſturbances of the
pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Peace and Safety, by what hand ſoever carryed on; ſo we do hold
it our duty further to Declare, That whoſoever ſhall be found (in
purſuance of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> the Scots King)
promoting the Intereſt of him the ſaid <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> or any way
engaging in the proſecution of the wicked Deſigns therein contained, They
ſhall be proceeded againſt with much more ſeverity then Delinquents in
the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Wars, as to the judgement of Parliament ſhall be thought
meet.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <p>SInce the dispatch of this Anſwer, there came to hand the Copies
of four Letters, written from the Earl of <hi>Loudoun,</hi> Chancellor of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> to the King of Scots, which were taken in the ſaid
Chancellors Cabinet among the ſpoils of the Scots, at the late memorable
defeat of their Army in the Fields of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar:</hi> By which ſeaſonable
Providence, a further diſcovery is made, of what was ſufficiently evident
before to all diſcerning men; both of the Scots continuing Deſign to invade
<hi>England,</hi> had we not thus prevented them; and of the diſſembling
formality of their Kings Repentance, ſo much cryed up by them, upon his
omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (as they call it) this Declaration, and obtruded upon their credulous
multitudes, and ſwallowed by their Party here for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt ſake: when
hereby 'tis evident 'twas drawn by them in <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,</hi> and extorted
from him with Minatory importunities, and well demonſtrates the little
ſenſe of Conſcience or Honor in that Kings, &amp; the desperateneſs of
his hopes that purſues his end by ſuch means. And it may further be
obſerved, what ſincerity can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <pb n="37" facs="tcp:117902:19"/>from that
Nation in any Publique Tranſactions, when their great Miniſter of State
dare make ſo bold with his Kings Anſwer, as to alter it to what he thought
would be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter ſerve a turn; and
offer that to their Parliament as their Kings, with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut ever conſulting him in it, and that
in a buſineſs of ſo great a concernment: The diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of theſe
juglings may be uſeful for thoſe who have been impoſed upon by the
boldneſs of theſe Inſtruments, who without reſpect or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to truth, are wont to be bold with any
thing that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to their end.</p>
            <div type="license">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Die Veneris, 20 Septembr. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Copy of a Letter from the Lord <hi>Loudoun</hi> to the King
of <hi>Scotland,</hi> dated 9 <hi>Julii,</hi> 1650, and the Copies of three
other Letters, all found in the Lord <hi>Loudouns</hi> Cabinet, were all this
day Read.</p>
               <p>ORdered by the Parliament, That the ſaid four Letters be
all printed at the latter end of the Declara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, with the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances when and where the ſame were found;
And it is referred to Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> to take care to ſee them printed
accordingly.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric.  Parliamenti.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt Gracious Soveraign,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ALbeit there be no man rejoyces more for your Majeſties ſafe
Arrival in this Kingdom, or more deſirous to wait upon your Majeſty then my
ſelf; yet the duty of my place in attending the Parliament ſo long as it
was ſitting (where I did endeavor to be more ſerviceable to your Majeſty
then I could be elſewhere) and the diſtemper of my health, not permiting me
to travel, I hope will plead pardon at your Majeſties hand, that I have not
come to wait upon you; but ſo ſoon as I ſhall be any ways able to travel,
I ſhall attend your Majeſty; and ſhall not preſume to trouble your
Majeſty with any particulars till then, reſolving to make it my chief care
and ſtudy how to improve the happy agreement (laid upon ſo pious and well
grounded a Foundation of a Covenant with God and your People) to the beſt
advantage, as may conduce <pb n="38" facs="tcp:117902:20"/>moſt to his Honor, and the
Recovery of your Majeſties juſt and undoubted Right of all your Kingdoms;
than which, nothing ſhall be more faithfully and really endeavored by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Loyal Subject and humble
Servant, LOUDOUN.</signed> 
                  <dateline>Edinburgh, 
<date>9 Julii, 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Endorſed,</hi> A Copy of my Letter to the Kings
Majeſty,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>9 Julii, 1650.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt gracious Soveraign,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Marqueſs of <hi>Argyle</hi> and the Earl
<hi>Balclewgh,</hi> have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to me your Majeſties Anſwer to that
Paper, which was preſented by him and others to your Majeſty, in Name of
your Parliament and their Committee, concerning the Removal of ſome of your
Servants and others from your Court and Royal Perſon: And conſidering that
ſome parts of your Anſwer is ſuch as would not be Satisfactory, I have
preſumed to alter it, and write it ſo, as I am confident will give good
Satisfaction: For ſeeing your Majeſty hath by your Anſwer to the ſame
Deſires, given full contentment to the General Aſſembly, I doubt not but
your Majeſty is willing to give the ſame conent to your Parliament and
Committee of Eſtates: Therefore I truſt your Majeſty will pardon my
boldneſs, for I know no better ſervice can be done to your Majeſty, than
that any thing which proceeds from you, may be acceptable to your People, and
that your Majeſty may be more and more endeared in their affections; which is
the duty, and ſhall be ever the deſire of</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Endorſed,</hi> A Copy of my Letter to the King,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>July 22. 1650.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt gracious Soveraign,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe condition of your Majeſties Army here, and what our
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions are at preſent, will be ſo exactly ſhewn to your
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty by Sir <hi>James Lumſden,</hi> as I ſhall refer the particulars
to his Relations, rather than trouble your Majeſty with a long Letter; yet
briefly I hold it fit to ſhew your Majeſty, That <hi>Cromwel</hi> hath
gotten more than a moneths proviſion for his Army by Sea, and 
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117902:20"/>that he expects ſhortly new Recruits: And victuals being
ſo ſcarce, as it will be very difficult to entertain our Army in a Body
till the Harveſt, that Corns be cut and reaped, Its reſolved, for this and
other Reaſons, That this Army ſhall march out to the fields nearer the
Enemy, and (if they force us to fight) in Gods ſtrength to give them Battel;
or (if they ſhall not purſue us) ſome Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe will be undertaken,
to make a diverſion to give the Enemy work in <hi>England,</hi> rather than
conſume us with a lingring War, and make the ſeat of it in
<hi>Scotland.</hi> In order to which, your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties haſtning hither your
Declaration is ſo neceſſary, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of it will retard and
obſtruct any Expedition into <hi>England;</hi> and time is ſo precious, as
the loſs of opportunity can hardly ever be recovered: So praying God to
bleſs your Majeſty, and ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect your Councels, and the actions of your
Armies, as may ſerve moſt for his honor, &amp; may reſtore your Majeſty
to your juſt Right. And, <hi>Sir,</hi> It is the deſire and judgement of
many, That Sir <hi>J. L.</hi> ſhould be Lieut: General of the Foot, but was
not thought expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to do it preſently, to ſhun conteſt and emulation;
yet his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Cauſe, and to your Majeſties Service, is ſuch,
as he is willing to give his beſt aſſiſtance in ordering the Army, and
to act his part in a day of Battel: And truly <hi>Sir,</hi> he is a perſon of
ſo much valor and experience in War, that your Majeſty would give him all
encouragement, and lay your Commands upon him, to return pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to the
Army, and not leave it.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Endorſed,</hi> A Scroll of my Letter to the King,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Aug. 10. 1650.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THere hath been ſo much ſaid by theſe who are here, and
thoſe were ſent from the Committee of Eſtates, and from the
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the General Aſſembly, to move your Majeſty to emit
that Declaration for ſatisfaction of the Church and State, and of ſuch in
all your Kingdoms as deſire Religion and your Majeſtics Throne to be
eſtabliſh'd, according to the Covenant, as I can adde little to perſwade
your Majeſty; yet if your Majeſty ſhall ponder in the Ballance of
righteous judgement, the conſequences will follow upon your granting or
refuſal, your Majeſty will not deny it. If your Majeſty grant and emit
this Declaration, you <pb n="40" facs="tcp:117902:21"/>ſatisfie the Church, the State, the
Army, and all your gude Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; They all concur to act for you, and the Army
is ready (if they be not engaged in preſent Battel) to march into
<hi>England,</hi> and leave <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all which is dear to them to
the utmoſt hazard, and ſacrifice their Lives for carrying on the Work of
Reformation, and reſtoring your Majeſty to your Right and Crown of
<hi>England:</hi> And then, if there be any in <hi>England</hi> who dare appear
for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for their own Liberties, or for your Majeſties Intereſt,
they will finde a fit opportunity for it. Your Majeſty is now obliged by the
Oath of Covenant with God and your People, to promote the Ends of the Covenant
in your Royal Station and Place, to the utmoſt of your Power. And your
Majeſty by the Treaty with this Kingdom, and in gude Reaſon, is bund to
follow the Counſel and Advice of your Parliament and Church, and of theſe
who are by them authorized; and ſince this which is earneſtly deſired by
both, as neceſſary for the good of Religion and the Covenant, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging
of the Church and Kingdom to hazard their Lives and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates for carrying on
your Majeſties Intereſt, with the Intereſt of Religion, your Majeſty
ſhould not deny, but cordially and ſpeedily condeſcend to it.</p>
               <p>If your Majeſty, after ſo earneſt intreaty and ſuch
offers, from the Church, the State and the Army, ſhall refuſe to ſatisfie
the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and clear your Reſolutions, your Majeſty will grieve their
Spirits, cool their Affections, and weaken their Hands: And ſince your
Majeſty refuſeth to do what is neceſſary for the good of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and
Gods Intereſt, they will look to the ſafety and good of Religion, and to
their own Safety, and emit a Declaration, how willing they are to hazard their
lives for your Majeſties Intereſt, if ye had been for Religion; but that
being denyed, they will ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the preſervation of Religion from your
Intereſt, and ſo to the Safety of this Kingdom; and if there be a
difference and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration upon thoſe grounds, there will never, in humane
appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, be ſuch a conjunction, and your Enemies (who will grant any
thing which may deſtroy your Majeſty) will win their ends.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Endorſed,</hi> A Copy of my Letter to his Majeſty,
upon ſending the Declaration to him to be Signed.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
